<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ramblings of a geeky Elvis.]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.red-elvis.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.red-elvis.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-18T10:19:29+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.red-elvis.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrés Gasson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NTP]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.red-elvis.net/2011/02/01/ntp/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-01T09:51:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.red-elvis.net/2011/02/01/ntp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;h2&gt;Information&lt;/h2&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;SNTP: Client-only version of NTP (NTP Server -&amp;gt; SNTP Client). Can use unicast or broadcast..&lt;/p&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;p&gt;NTP: Client and Server, uses UDP port 123. Uses unicast by default (client does a GET) but can also run in broadcast and multicast (224.0.1.1) mode (make sure you enable multicast routing in that case).&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;Stratum: Indicates the quality of the time source. Lower is better, default is 8. Stratum 1 is normally atomic good…&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;Some NTP commands are at the global level, and some at the interface level. &lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;NTP is supposed to be a simple topic but, for some reason it had me pulling a lot of hair out. The best advice I can give is to be patient with updates…&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;h2&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
   &lt;h3&gt;100% Foolproof Config&lt;/h3&gt;</p>

<p>&lt;table width=”100%” border=”0” cellpadding=”0” cellspacing=”0” class=”tiny”&gt;
     &lt;tr class=”tableTitle”&gt;
       &lt;td class=”code”&gt;&lt;strong class=”tiny”&gt;Server Side&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;From &lt;a href=”http://www-tac.cisco.com/Support_Library/Internetworking/NTP/mailarchive/0003.html”&gt;Dave Katz in his TAC days&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
     &lt;/tr&gt;
     &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td class=”code”&gt;R1#clock set 12:00:00 1 jan 2005 &lt;/td&gt;</p>

<pre><code>   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R1(config)#clock timezone EST -5 &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R1(config)#clock summertine EDT recurring &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;

   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span class="style1"&amp;gt;R1(config)#ntp master [stratum]&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;To enable NTP server&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%" class="code"&amp;gt;R1(config)#clock-calendar valid&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;

   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;Tells the router to trust the internal clock (authoritative - only for platforms with real-time clocks )&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R1(config)#ntp authenticate &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;To enable NTP authentication on server&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;

   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R1(config)#ntp trusted-key 1 &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;To define which key(s) will be accepted.&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R1(config)#ntp authentication-key 1 md5 cisco123 &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;To define key(s) (multiple keys can be defined for migrations, etc.).&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top" class="tableTitle"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%" class="code"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong class="tiny"&amp;gt;Client Side&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R2(config)#clock timezone EST -5 &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R2(config)#clock summertine EDT recurring &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%" class="code"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;span class="style1"&amp;gt;R2(config)#ntp server &amp;amp;lt;ip address&amp;amp;gt; [key]&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To enable NTP client and associate with a key. &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%" class="code"&amp;gt;R2(config)#ntp update-calendar&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;

   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;(updade the internal RT clock - only for platforms with real-time clocks)&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td class="code"&amp;gt;R2(config)#ntp authentication-key 1 md5 cisco123 &amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td&amp;gt;To define key(s) (multiple keys can be defined for migrations, etc.).&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;    &amp;lt;/table&amp;gt;
</code></pre>

<p>&lt;h3&gt;Commands&lt;/h3&gt;
   &lt;table width=”100%” border=”0” cellspacing=”2” cellpadding=”1”&gt;
     &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td width=”50%”&gt;R1(config)#ntp master &amp;lt;stratum&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td width=”50%”&gt;To enable NTP server.&lt;/td&gt;
     &lt;/tr&gt;
     &lt;tr valign=”top”&gt;</p>

<pre><code>   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R1(config-if)#ntp broadcast&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To use broadcast (or multicast *need multicast routing).&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;

   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R2(config)#ntp server &amp;amp;lt;ip address&amp;amp;gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To enable NTP client (one-way sync) in unicast mode.&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R2(config-if)#ntp broadcast client&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To enable NTP client in broadcast mode (or multicast *need multicast routing).&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R2(config-if)#ntp disable&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To disable NTP on an interface.&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R3(config)#ntp peer &amp;amp;lt;ip address&amp;amp;gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To enable NTP peering (two-way sync).&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R3(config)#ntp peer &amp;amp;lt;ip address&amp;amp;gt; prefer&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To define who is better.&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;

   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R1(config)#ntp access-group [query-only|serve-only|serve|peer] &amp;amp;lt;access-list 1-99&amp;amp;gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To configure NTP Security.&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;&amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R4(config)#sntp server &amp;amp;lt;ip address&amp;amp;gt;&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To enable/configure SNTP server (unicast mode).&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;

 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;tr valign="top"&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;R4(config-if)#sntp broadcast client&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;td width="50%"&amp;gt;To enable SNTP (broadcast mode).&amp;lt;/td&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/tr&amp;gt;    &amp;lt;/table&amp;gt;    &amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;Links&amp;lt;/h2&amp;gt;
</code></pre>

<p>&lt;p&gt;NTP Overview/Architecture&lt;br /&gt;
   &lt;a href=”http://www.cisco.com/univercd/cc/td/doc/product/iaabu/cddm/cddm111/adguide/ntp.htm#xtocid189301”&gt;http://www.cisco.com/univercd/cc/td/doc/product/iaabu/cddm/cddm111/adguide/ntp.htm#xtocid189301&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;NTP Configuration&lt;br /&gt;
     &lt;a href=”http://www.cisco.com/univercd/cc/td/doc/product/software/ios122/122cgcr/ffun_c/fcfprt3/fcf012.htm”&gt;http://www.cisco.com/univercd/cc/td/doc/product/software/ios122/122cgcr/ffun_c/fcfprt3/fcf012.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
   Hardening Cisco Routers - Chapter 10 - NTP&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;a href=”http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/hardcisco/chapter/ch10.html”&gt;http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/hardcisco/chapter/ch10.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!– InstanceEndEditable –&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IPv6 Notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.red-elvis.net/2011/01/25/ipv6/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-25T23:30:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.red-elvis.net/2011/01/25/ipv6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>**IPv6 Address formats **</p>

<p>Table 2 Compressed IPv6 Address Formats</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>IPv6 Address Type</td>
      <td>Preferred Format</td>
      <td>Compressed Format</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Unicast</td>
      <td>2001:0:0:0:0DB8:800:200C:417A</td>
      <td>2001::0DB8:800:200C:417A</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Multicast</td>
      <td>FF01:0:0:0:0:0:0:101</td>
      <td>FF01::101</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Loopback</td>
      <td>0:0:0:0:0:0:0:1</td>
      <td>::1</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Unspecified</td>
      <td>0:0:0:0:0:0:0:0</td>
      <td>::</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The loopback address listed in <a href="#wp1016337">Table 2</a> may be used by a node to send an
IPv6 packet to itself. The loopback address in IPv6 functions the same as the
loopback address in IPv4 (127.0.0.1). The IPv6 loopback address cannot be
assigned to a physical interface. A packet that has the IPv6 loopback address
as its source or destination address must remain within the node that created
the packet. IPv6 routers do not forward packets that have the IPv6 loopback
address as their source or destination address. The unspecified address listed
in Table 2 indicates the absence of an IPv6 address. For example, a newly
initialized node on an IPv6 network may use the unspecified address as the
source address in its packets until it receives its IPv6 address.</p>

<p><strong>Aggregatable Global Address</strong></p>

<p>An aggregatable global address is an IPv6 address from the aggregatable global
unicast prefix. The structure of aggregatable global unicast addresses enables
strict aggregation of routing prefixes that limits the number of routing table
entries in the global routing table. Aggregatable global addresses are used on
links that are aggregated upward through organizations, and eventually to the
Internet service providers (ISPs). Aggregatable global IPv6 addresses are
defined by a global routing prefix, a subnet ID, and an interface ID. Except
for addresses that start with binary 000, all global unicast addresses have a
64-bit interface ID. The current global unicast address allocation uses the
range of addresses that start with binary value 001 (2000::/3). Figure 2 shows
the structure of an aggregatable global address.</p>

<p><strong>Figure 2 Aggregatable Global Address Format</strong></p>

<p><img src="./AggregatableAddresses.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Addresses with a prefix of 2000::/3 (001) through E000::/3 (111) are required
to have 64-bit interface identifiers in the extended universal identifier
(EUI)-64 format. The Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) allocates the
IPv6 address space in the range of 2000::/16 to regional registries.</p>

<p>The aggregatable global address typically consists of a 48-bit global routing
prefix and a 16-bit subnet ID or Site-Level Aggregator (SLA). In the IPv6
aggregatable global unicast address format document (RFC 2374), the global
routing prefix included two other hierarchically structured fields named Top-
Level Aggregator (TLA) and Next-Level Aggregator (NLA).The IETF decided to
remove the TLS and NLA fields from the RFCs, because these fields are policy-
based. Some existing IPv6 networks deployed before the change might still be
using networks based on the older architecture.</p>

<p>A 16-bit subnet field called the subnet ID could be used by individual
organizations to create their own local addressing hierarchy and to identify
subnets. A subnet ID is similar to a subnet in IPv4, except that an
organization with an IPv6 subnet ID can support up to 65,535 individual
subnets.</p>

<p>An interface ID is used to identify interfaces on a link. The interface ID
must be unique to the link. It may also be unique over a broader scope. In
many cases, an interface ID is the same as or based on the link-layer address
of an interface. Interface IDs used in aggregatable global unicast and other
IPv6 address types must be 64 bits long and constructed in the modified EUI-64
format.</p>

<p>Interface IDs are constructed in the modified EUI-64 format in one of the
following ways:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>For all IEEE 802 interface types (for example, Ethernet interfaces and
FDDI interfaces), the first three octets (24 bits) are taken from the
Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI) of the 48-bit link-layer address (MAC
address) of the interface, the fourth and fifth octets (16 bits) are a fixed
hexadecimal value of FFFE, and the last three octets (24 bits) are taken from
the last three octets of the MAC address. The construction of the interface ID
is completed by setting the Universal/Local (U/L) bit–the seventh bit of the
first octet–to a value of 0 or 1. A value of 0 indicates a locally
administered identifier; a value of 1 indicates a globally unique IPv6
interface identifier. ie To denote unique interface address, flip the 2nd bit in the first octet:
0000 0000 (00) to 0000 0010 (02)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>For all other interface types (for example, serial, loopback, ATM,
Frame Relay, and tunnel interface types–except tunnel interfaces used with
IPv6 overlay tunnels), the interface ID is constructed in the same way as the
interface ID for IEEE 802 interface types; however, the first MAC address from
the pool of MAC addresses in the router is used to construct the identifier
(because the interface does not have a MAC address).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>For tunnel interface types that are used with IPv6 overlay tunnels, the
interface ID is the IPv4 address assigned to the tunnel interface with all
zeros in the high-order 32 bits of the identifier.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<ul>
  <li>**Note ** For interfaces using PPP, given that the interfaces at both
ends of the connection might have the same MAC address, the interface
identifiers used at both ends of the connection are negotiated (picked
randomly and, if necessary, reconstructed) until both identifiers are unique.
The first MAC address in the router is used to construct the identifier for
interfaces using PPP.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>If no IEEE 802 interface types are in the router, link-local IPv6 addresses
are generated on the interfaces in the router in the following sequence:</p>

<p><strong>Link-local Addresses</strong></p>

<p>A link-local address is an IPv6 unicast address that can be automatically
configured on any interface using the link-local prefix FE80::/10 (1111 1110
10) and the interface identifier in the modified EUI-64 format. Link-local
addresses are used in the neighbor discovery protocol and the stateless
autoconfiguration process. Nodes on a local link can use link-local addresses
to communicate; the nodes do not need site-local or globally unique addresses
to communicate. Figure 3 shows the structure of a link-local address.</p>

<p>IPv6 routers must not forward packets that have link-local source or
destination addresses to other links.</p>

<p><strong>Figure 3 Link-local Address Format</strong></p>

<p><img src="./LinklocalAddresses.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>IPv4-Compatible IPv6 Addresses</strong></p>

<p>An IPv4-compatible IPv6 address is an IPv6 unicast address that has zeros in
the high-order 96 bits of the address and an IPv4 address in the low-order 32
bits of the address. The format of an IPv4-compatible IPv6 address is
0:0:0:0:0:0:A.B.C.D or ::A.B.C.D. The entire 128-bit IPv4-compatible IPv6
address is used as the IPv6 address of a node and the IPv4 address embedded in
the low-order 32 bits is used as the IPv4 address of the node. IPv4-compatible
IPv6 addresses are assigned to nodes that support both the IPv4 and IPv6
protocol stacks and are used in automatic tunnels. Figure 4 shows the
structure of an IPv4-compatible IPv6 address and a few acceptable formats for
the address.</p>

<p><strong>Figure 4 IPv4-Compatible IPv6 Address Format</strong></p>

<p><img src="./IPv4Compatible.jpg" alt="IPv4-Compatible IPv6 Address Format" /></p>

<p><strong>IPv6 Multicast Address</strong></p>

<p>An IPv6 multicast address is an IPv6 address that has a prefix of FF00::/8
(1111 1111). An IPv6 multicast address is an identifier for a set of
interfaces that typically belong to different nodes. A packet sent to a
multicast address is delivered to all interfaces identified by the multicast
address. The second octet following the prefix defines the lifetime and scope
of the multicast address. A permanent multicast address has a lifetime
parameter equal to 0; a temporary multicast address has a lifetime parameter
equal to 1. A multicast address that has the scope of a node, link, site, or
organization, or a global scope has a scope parameter of 1, 2, 5, 8, or E,
respectively. For example, a multicast address with the prefix FF02::/16 is a
permanent multicast address with a link scope. Figure 5 shows the format of
the IPv6 multicast address.</p>

<p><strong>Figure 5 Multicast Address Format</strong></p>

<p><img src="./Multicast.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>IPv6 nodes (hosts and routers) are required to join (receive packets destined
for) the following multicast groups:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All-nodes multicast group FF02:0:0:0:0:0:0:1 (scope is link-local)</li>
  <li>Solicited-node multicast group FF02:0:0:0:0:1:FF00:0000/104 for each of its
assigned unicast and anycast addresses</li>
</ul>

<p>IPv6 routers must also join the all-routers multicast group FF02:0:0:0:0:0:0:2
(scope is link-local).</p>

<p>The solicited-node multicast address is a multicast group that corresponds to
an IPv6 unicast or anycast address. IPv6 nodes must join the associated
solicited-node multicast group for every unicast and anycast address to which
it is assigned. The IPv6 solicited-node multicast address has the prefix
FF02:0:0:0:0:1:FF00:0000/104 concatenated with the 24 low-order bits of a
corresponding IPv6 unicast address. (See Figure 6.) For example, the
solicited-node multicast address corresponding to the IPv6 address
2037::01:800:200E:8C6C is FF02::1:FF0E:8C6C. Solicited-node addresses are used
in neighbor solicitation messages</p>

<p><img src="./Ipv6SolicitedNodeMulticast.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The basic IPv6 packet header has 8 fields with a total size of 40 octets (320
bits). (See Figure 7.) Fields were removed from the IPv6 header because, in
IPv6, fragmentation is not handled by routers and checksums at the network
layer are not used. Instead, fragmentation in IPv6 is handled by the source of
a packet and checksums at the data link layer and transport layer are used.
(In IPv4, the User Datagram Protocol (UDP) transport layer uses an optional
checksum. In IPv6, use of the UDP checksum is required to check the integrity
of the inner packet.) Additionally, the basic IPv6 packet header and Options
field are aligned to 64 bits, which can facilitate the processing of IPv6
packets.</p>

<p><img src="./IPv6pkt.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h3 id="table-4-ipv6-extension-header-types">Table 4 IPv6 Extension Header Types</h3>

<p>|:—————|:——————-|:—————————————————|
|<strong>Header Type</strong>|<strong>Next Header Value</strong>|<strong>Description</strong>|
|Hop-by-hop options header|0|This header is processed by all hops in the path of a packet. When present,the hop-by-hop options header always follows immediately after the basic IPv6 packet header.|
|Destination options header|60|The destination options header can follow any hop-by-hop options header, in which case the destination options header is processed at the final
destination and also at each visited address specified by a routing header. Alternatively, the destination options header can follow any Encapsulating
Security Payload (ESP) header, in which case the destination options header is processed only at the final destination.|
|Routing header|43|The routing header is used for source routing.
|Fragment header|44|The fragment header is used when a source must fragment a packet that is larger than the maximum transmission unit (MTU) for the path between itself
and a destination. The Fragment header is used in each fragmented packet.
|Authentication header and ESP header|51 or 50|The Authentication header and the ESP header are used within IP Security Protocol (IPSec) to provide authentication, integrity, and confidentiality of a packet. These headers are identical for both IPv4 and IPv6.
|Upper-layer header</p>

<p>6 (TCP)</p>

<p>17 (UDP)</p>

<p>The upper-layer (transport) headers are the typical headers used inside a
packet to transport the data. The two main transport protocols are TCP and
UDP.</p>

<p>Mobility header</p>

<p>To be done by IANA</p>

<p>Extension headers used by mobile nodes, correspondent nodes, and home agents
in all messaging related to the creation and management of bindings.</p>

<p>8 set of hexadecimal numbers separated by :</p>

<p>2 character = 1 byte</p>

<p>First 64 bit for network and last 64 bit for host (calculated automatically)</p>

<p>Leading bits tell what class – format prefix (FP)</p>

<p>Aggregate global unicast 001 2000 – 3FFF</p>

<p>Link-local unicast 1111 1110 10 FEC0</p>

<p>Site-local unicast 1111 1110 11 FE80</p>

<p>Multicast 1111 1111 FF</p>

<p>Gap in there is unassigned for future …</p>

<p>Auto-generation of host address done using this algorithm</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Take MAC – 1234.5678.9012</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Invert 7th most significant digit – 1034.5678.9012</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Insert FFFE in the middle – 1034:56FF:FE78:9012</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>And this gives us the modified EUI</p>

<h1 id="address-resolution">Address resolution</h1>

<p>No ARP anymore. ICMPv6 ND (neighbor discovery) instead</p>

<p>NBMA – multipoint need address resolution. must do statically today because
inverse neighbor discovery not in IOS yet.</p>

<p>ICMPv6 ND has four communication types</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>NS (neighbor solicitation): ask for info on the neighbors</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>NA (neighbor advertisement): advertise self to other neighbors</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>RS (router solicitation): ask for local routers</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>RA (router advertisement): advertise self as active router</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Startup process</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Select a link local address (FEC0 + 64bit EUI)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Send NS to solicited node multicast FF02::1:FFxx:xxxx:/104 + 24 lower
order bits (last 6 digits of above link local address)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Send this for our link local and global address to see if we are unique</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If no reply back, then have unique address – DAD (duplicate address
detection)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In this case, send unsolicited NA to all host multicast saying I am active
– FF02::1 (same as 255.255.255.255 – local link broadcast)</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>No concept of proxy ICMPv6 ND (equivalent to proxy arp). Reason is because we
send it to solicited node multicast address in IPv6 vs. broadcast address in
IPv4. So if router was to try to run proxy ICMPv6 ND would have to join every
possible multicast solicited node address</p>

<p>To enable IPv6 on an interface use the i<strong>pv6 enable</strong> command. We haven’t
assigned an IP at this point so only link-local processing enabled.</p>

<p><strong>Show ipv6 neighbor</strong> is same as <strong>show ip arp</strong> in IPv4</p>

<p>If assign a global address on a router, it will start broadcasting that for
autoconfig. So when host comes up, it will know what prefix to use for itself.
Can even enable autoconfig address on router using <strong>ipv6 address autoconfig</strong></p>

<p>If we set static route pointing to the interface to go out of, then we have an
address resolution issue. Need to make a static binding pointing the L3
address to the next-hop MAC. On ethernet static binding is **ipv6 neighbor
**<em>address interface MAC</em> since no proxy ARP equivalent. May work for a couple
of hosts but won’t scale.</p>

<h1 id="routing">Routing</h1>

<p>RIPng and OSPF use separate process from v4</p>

<p>BGP and IS-IS use same process as v4</p>

<h1 id="ripng">RIPng</h1>

<p>UDP 521 multicast to FF02::9</p>

<p>Enabled per interface using <strong>ipv6 rip <em>process-name</em> enable</strong></p>

<p>Routing recourses to remote link local address. So when looking in routing
table it will show the link local address as the next-hop.</p>

<p>On FR need to map the link-local and global unicast address to the DLCI.
Ultimately need the link local to route and forward packets so definitely need
them.</p>

<p>Can hard-configure the link local address using <strong>ipv6 address **<em>address</em></strong>
link-local**</p>

<p>Split-horizon is enabled by default. Disabled at the process level not
interface level</p>

<p>Clearing routing table no longer refreshes the dynamic routes. Need to clear
the routing process using **clear ipv6 rip **<em>process-name</em></p>

<p>ND – ARP … so ethernet only</p>

<h1 id="ospfv3">OSPFv3</h1>

<p>Similar to OSPFv2</p>

<p>Router-id is still an IPv4 address. So if no IPv4 address on an interface in
up/up, issue router-id command and give it one. Similar issue with BGP</p>

<p>Can enable globally or if you enable on interface using i<strong>pv6 ospf
**<em>process-id</em></strong> area **<em>area</em> it also enables it globally. No network
command.</p>

<p>Same network types as IPv4. When unicast’ing, sending to link-local so make
sure they are reachable. Also, neighbor command is done at interface level
using <strong>ipv6 ospf neighbor **<em>link-local-address</em></strong>**</p>

<p>Again non-broadcast network recourses to link local address so need to map
those to DLCI too. Way to avoid all these maps is to run it as point-to-
multipoint. In this case update next-hop and use MAC address of next-hop (hub)
and so just need map statement for that MAC.</p>

<h1 id="bgp">BGP</h1>

<p>Similar to IPv4. Configured under same process using the <strong>address-family</strong>
class. Similar to MPLS with VRF’s. Configure neighbor statement as before with
remote-as, but then need to activate them.</p>

<p><strong>Router bgp **<em>process</em></strong>**</p>

<p><strong>Neighbor **<em>address</em></strong> remote-as <strong><em>As</em></strong>**</p>

<p><strong>address-family ipv6</strong></p>

<p><strong>neighbor **<em>address</em></strong> activate**</p>

<p>By default, all ipv4 address are automatically activated because <strong>bgp default
ipv4-unicast</strong> is on by default.</p>

<h1 id="tunneling">Tunneling</h1>

<p>Static</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>GRE – default tunnel mode. Can encapsulate a lot more protocols</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>IPv6IP – less overhead, no CLNS transport</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Automatic</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>6to4 – imbed IPv4 in IPv6 prefix to provide automatic tunnel
endpoint determination</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>ISATAP – automatic host to router and host to host tunneling. Tunnel
IPv6 over IPv6</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>GRE is same as before, just with ipv6 address</p>

<p>Tunnel mode sets which of above</p>

<p>6to4:</p>

<p>Derive IPv6 address as 2002:_IPv4-address_::/48</p>

<p>Single /48 subnetted amongst sites</p>

<p>Only one tunnel needed for all destinations</p>

<p>Dynamically figure out tunnel destination from the IPv6 address</p>

<p>Source of the tunnel has to be the interface embedded as IPv4 address</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PIM Study Notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.red-elvis.net/2011/01/07/pim/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-07T23:02:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.red-elvis.net/2011/01/07/pim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="pim-neigbour-discovery">PIM Neigbour Discovery</h2>
<p>PIM routers send PIM Hello messages every 30 seconds on each PIM enabled interface.  The Hellos are sent to 224.0.0.13, the link local address reserved for All-PIM-Routers</p>

<h2 id="pim-dr">PIM DR</h2>
<p>Hellos are used to find neighbors, and to determine who should be the Designated Router (DR) on multi-access networks.  If no DR priority configured, then the PIM router with the highest IP address wins.  In PIM Sparse Mode, the DR is responsible for registering to the RP, and forwarding traffic.</p>

<h2 id="pim-asserts">PIM Asserts</h2>
<p>If a router sees traffic for a stream coming in on an interface it uses to forward traffic for the stream, it will send an Assert message on that interface.   The assert contains administrative distance and metric information for the route in the murib for the source of the stream.  First administrative distance is compared.  If equal, metric is compared.  If the metric is also equal, than the peer with the highest IP address wins. The loser prunes itself off the path for the stream.</p>

<h2 id="pim-sm">PIM SM</h2>
<p>A PIM router creates (S,G) state under the following conditions</p>

<ul>
  <li>Traffic is seen on a directly connected interface.
Examples: DR, routers in path down RPT from RP to LH</li>
  <li>An RP receives a Register message.</li>
  <li>A Join for the (S,G) is received.</li>
</ul>

<p>A PIM router forwards (S,G) Joins towards the source when</p>

<ul>
  <li>The (S,G) has a valid outgoing interface list (olist) and the           router has RPF information for the source.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="pim-ssm">PIM SSM</h2>
<p>If IGMP knows the sources it wants to receive, it can inform it’s router.  PIM can then forward joins directly to the source.  PIM-SSM takes this a step further by outlawing (*,G) state in the SSM range.  Not only isn’t an RP required, it’s prohibited.</p>

<p>232.0.0.0/8 is the default range for SSM, but it can be configured to any other range as well. Currently though 232/8 is hardwired in our (XR, IOS?) IGMP implementation, so no (*,G) IGMP reports will be accepted in that range.</p>

<p>These rules are directly from the PIM spec.</p>

<ul>
  <li>A router MUST NOT send a (*,G) Join/Prune message for any reason.</li>
  <li>A router MUST NOT send an (S,G,rpt) Join/Prune message for any reason.</li>
  <li>A router MUST NOT send a Register message for any packet that is
  destined to an SSM address.</li>
  <li>A router MUST NOT forward packets based on (*,G) or (S,G,rpt) state.
The (*,G) and (S,G,rpt) -related state summarization macros are NULL for any SSM address, for the purposes of packet forwarding.</li>
  <li>A router acting as an RP MUST NOT forward any Register-encapsulated packet that has an SSM destination address</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="pim-bidir">PIM-BIDIR</h2>
<p>PIM-BIDIR makes the RPT bidirectional.   The RP is the hub of all traffic, though traffic does not have to go all the way to the RP to reach local leaf nodes.  BIDIR forwards on (*,G) routes.</p>

<p>Simpler than PIM-SM.  No data driven events (eg, S,G creation based on data, KAT).</p>

<p>New sources are forwarded on the path to the RP (called the (*,G/M) route.</p>

<p>New (*,G) joins propagate towards the RP, and inherit accepting information from the RP.  The joins will create outgoing interface information – pointing back towards the LH (Last Hop).</p>

<h2 id="msdp">MSDP</h2>
<p>MSDP listens to PIM register messages, and if PIM installs an L flag for the route in the MRIB, MSDP sends the traffic in the registers encapsulated in Source Active (SA) messages to it’s configured peers.</p>

<p>If the remote RP has local receivers for the (S,G), it installs the route into the PIM topology table and forwards the traffic down the RPT.  The LH router performs SPT switchover.</p>

<p>If the remote RP has no local PIM interest in the SA, the SA stays in the MSDP cache but is not installed in PIM.</p>

<p>An SA contains the (S,G) info, the RP that originated the SA, and the encapsulated data sent in the register.</p>

<p>MSDP can be thought of as a poor man’s BGP. It doesn’t have ASs (so NO good loop avoidance), and it doesn’t have policy other than filtering.  It uses the below set of rules to determine which peers to accept SAs from, based on the RP which originated the SA.
connect-source == peer address used
originator-id == RP address SA sent from.</p>

<p>1) The MSDP peer P’s connect-source is equal to the originator-id of the SA</p>

<p>2) The MSDP peer P’s connect-source is equal to the BGP NEXT-HOP of the active route for the originator-id of the SA</p>

<p>3) a) The active route for the originator-id of the SA is known via BGP and the MSDP peer P’s connect-source is equal to the BGP peering address of the peer who announced the route.</p>

<p>b) The active route for the originator-id of the SA is known via ISIS/OSPF and the MSDP peer P’s connect-source is equal to the IGP next hop for the route.</p>

<p>4) The MSDP peer P’s connect-source is in an AS in the AS-PATH of the active route for the originator-id of the SA, and has the highest IP address of the MSDP peer’s connect-sources which reside in ASs in that AS-PATH.</p>

<p>5) The MSDP peer P is configured as the static RPF-peer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
